Guide to the John Merle Coulter Papers 1845-1929
University of Chicago Library
Coulter, John Merle. Papers
1845-1929
2.0 linear feet (4 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
John Merle Coulter (1851-1928), botanist and chair of the Botany Department of the University of Chicago, 1896-1926. The Papers contain the correspondence and personal papers of Coulter’s parents, relating mainly to a brief missionary tour to China. The collection also includes letters and school mementos, drafts of many of Coulter's postwar lectures and articles, and miscellaneous papers relating to his activities during the last five years of his life.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
John Merle Coulter (1851-1928), was born in China to Presbyterian missionaries Moses and Caroline Coulter. According to official records at Hanover College and Indiana University, he received an AB (1870) and honorary PhD (1884) from Hanover College and an honorary PhD (1884) from Indiana University.
Coulter served as Professor of Natural Sciences at Hanover College from 1874 to 1879 and Professor of Biology at Wabash College from 1879 to 1891. From 1891 to 1893, he was President of Indiana State University, then of Lake Forest College, from 1893-1896. In 1896, he became Chair of the Botany Department at the University of Chicago, where he remained until his retirement in 1925. In retirement, Coulter worked with the Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research in Yonkers, New York.
In addition to his academic appointments, Coulter served as Assistant Geologist and Botanist for the Hayden Survey of what is now Yellowstone National Park (1872) and, in 1875, co-founded the Botanical Bulletin, soon renamed the Botanical Gazette. A staunch evolutionist and Presbyterian, he had a particular interest in the correlation of science and religion.
Scope Note
The John M. Coulter Papers contain the correspondence and personal papers of Coulter's parents. These items relate mainly to the brief missionary tour of the Coulters at the Presbyterian Mission at Ningbo, China, which was terminated by Moses Coulter's death in 1853. The collection also includes letters and school mementos, drafts of many of Coulter's postwar lectures and articles, and miscellaneous papers relating to his activities during the last five years of his life. These activities included a trip to China and Japan in 1923, a project to write biographies for college students of important men of science, and the directorship of Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research at Yonkers, New York.
The collection is divided into two series. Series I includes letters and personal papers evidently preserved by Mrs. Caroline E. Coulter relating mainly to the brief missionary tour of the Coulters at the Presbyterian Mission at Ningbo, China, which was terminated by Moses Coulter's death in 1853. Series II comprises the principal portion of the collection is made up of letters and school mementos preserved by John M. Coulter’s mother and his mother-in-law, Anna M. Gaylord, drafts of many of Coulter's postwar lectures and articles, and miscellaneous papers relating to his activities during the last five years of his life: a trip to China and Japan in 1923, a project to write biographies for college students of important men of science, and the directorship of Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research at Yonkers, New York.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Coulter, John Merle, 1851-1928; Geological and Geographical Survey of the Territories (U.S.); Yellowstone National Park; Botanists; Missionaries; Missionaries -- China
INVENTORY
- Series I: Moses and Caroline Coulter Papers
  This series includes letters and personal papers evidently preserved by Mrs. Caroline E. Coulter. They relate mainly to the brief missionary tour of the Coulters at the Presbyterian Mission at Ningbo, China, which was terminated by Moses Coulter's death in 1853. The highlight of this portion of the collection is a small group of letters written to Mrs. Coulter by friends still in Ningbo following her return to the United States in 1854 with her two small sons, John and Stanley (sometimes referred to as "Diddi" in the letters). These letters describe the continuing activities of the mission in the mid- and late 1850's and early 1860's and give some picture of the attitudes of the missionaries themselves.
  - Commonplace Book: "To Mrs. Cara E. Coulter from her Affectionate Husband Moses S. Coulter." Contains: 1) Essays by Moses Coulter, June-July, 1845. 2) Journal of a Voyage from New York to China kept by Caroline Coulter, 1849. 3) "The Battle," a poem by Moses Coulter, 1846. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diaries of Moses Coulter, Sept. 4, 1848-Jan. 1, 1849: Lettered "A" and "B". (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Will of Moses S. Coulter, Sept. 30, 1851. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to and from Moses S. Coulter. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fragment of a letter describing Moses Coulter's last illness, c. 1853. (The letter is unsigned, but it appears to be in Caroline Coulter's hand.) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mr. and Mrs. H. V. Rankin. 15 letters, 1854-1861. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Joseph K. Wright. 6 letters, 1853-1859. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mr. and Mrs. R. Q. Way. 9 letters, 1854-1870. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dr. and Mrs. D. B. McCartee. 8 letters, 1855-1874. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. E. A. Goddard. 2 letters and one fragment, 1856-57. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mr. and Mrs. A. P. Hopper. 2 letters, 1859. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Other missionary letters: Caroline A. Cobhold[?]. 1 letter, June 13, 1855. Unsigned. 1 letter, May 29, 1863. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jane Coulter to her daughter-in-law (Caroline) and her grandson, letters, 1853-1868. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Postcards addressed to Caroline Coulter from John Coulter and members of his family. 18 cards, none dated. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - John Coulter's children to their grandmother, Caroline Coulter, none dated. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous. 3 letters, 1 telegram. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters by Caroline Coulter. 3. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series II: Papers of John M. Coulter
  This series comprises the principal portion of the collection is made up of letters and school mementos preserved by John M. Coulter’s mother and his mother-in-law, Anna M. Gaylord, drafts of many of Coulter's postwar lectures and articles, and miscellaneous papers relating to his activities during the last five years of his life: a trip to China and Japan in 1923, a project to write biographies for college students of important men of science, and the directorship of Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research at Yonkers, New York.
  - Letters addressed to John Coulter by friends of his mother and by relatives. 4 letters, 1859-76. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - John M. Coulter to Caroline E. Coulter. 9 letters, 1872-79. 1862-70. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - John M. Coulter to Caroline E. Coulter and Georgie Gaylord Coulter. 3 letters, 1879-84. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - John M. Coulter to Georgie Gaylord [Coulter]. 7 letters, 1872-73. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - John M. Coulter to Caroline E. Coulter. 11 letters, 1872-73. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - John Coulter to Caroline E. Coulter. 6 letters, May-June, 1903. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - John Coulter to Caroline E. Coulter. 9 letters, July-August, 1903. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - John Coulter to Caroline E. Coulter. 12 letters, Sept.-Nov., 1903. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Others in family to Caroline Coulter. 8 letters, June-Oct., 1903. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Georgie Coulter to her mother, Anna M. Gaylord. 18 letters, May-Oct., 1903. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - John M. Coulter to Caroline Coulter. 22 letters, Oct., 1905 - March, 1906. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Other members of family to Caroline Coulter. 2 letters, Nov., 1905. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Georgie Coulter to Anna M. Gaylord. 21 letters, 1905-06. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - John M. Coulter to Caroline E. Coulter. 3 letters. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Compositions by John M. Coulter: "Lines dedicated to my mother on her 34th birthday, Mar. 24, 1862." "Description of Waveland Collegiate Institute." Feb., 1863. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Student Notebook: English Literature. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reports of Standing: Hanover College, 1866, 1868, 1870 (5 reports) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Certificate of Marriage: John M. Coulter to Georgie M. Gaylord. Jan. 1, 1874. Pasted in front of a copy of The Marriage Gift by James Petrie. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Botanical Gazette, edited by John M. and M. Stanley Coulter: Mailing list for 1889 and miscellaneous papers. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notebooks (2). Notes made on European trips of 1903 and 1905. (Back of 1905-06 notebook contains cancelled draft of an article on Asa Gray.) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - China -Japan Trip (1923-24): Itinerary. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - China-Japan Trip (1923-24): Postcards, photographs, and clippings. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Boyce Thompson Institute: Birthday greeting, Nov. 20, 1926, signed by members of staff. Copy of Contributions, Jan. 1, 1925. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica, correspondence concerning articles for. Sept., 1928. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notices. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Telegrams of sympathy. Testament of Hyde Park Men's Club. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters of sympathy. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Coulter's lapsed life insurance policy. Correspondence with Mutual Life Insurance, by Merle Coulter (son), Dec., 1928-Jan., 1929. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letter to Merle Coulter, concerning his share in estate. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - List of addresses and papers (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Botanical Opportunity (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Botany as a National Asset (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Development of Botany in the United States (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Evolution of Botanical Research (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Evolution of Plants (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Future of Botany (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The New Botany (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Biological Background of Religious Education (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Case for Religions (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Christianity and Science (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Cooperation of Science and Religion (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Evolution and Christianity (another version of folder 12) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Evolution and its Explanations (reprint from Christian Century, May 22, 1922.) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The History of Organic Evolution (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Meaning of Evolution (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The Methods and Results of Science (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Need for Cooperation (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Original Exploration of Yellowstone National Park (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Our National Park (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - The Personal Faith of a Scientist (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - The Present Status of Organic Evolution (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - The Role of Science in Modern Civilization (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - The Science of Religion (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Welcoming talk: "It is a great pleasure to the Institute Staff to welcome this group of Chemists..." (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Welcoming talk: "It is a great pleasure to welcome this group of pathologists..." (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research (another version) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Research at the Boyce Thompson Institute (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Work of the Boyce Thompson Institute (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Otis Caldwell to John M. Coulter. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with scientists concerning source material for biographies. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Writings, 1896-1916, "The Botanical Outlook," 1895 "The Embryo Sac and Embryo of Gnetum Gnemon," 1908 "Evolutionary Tendencies among Gymnosperms," 1909 "Inheritance Through Spores," 1916 "Some College Fallacies," 1900 (Box 4, Folder 8.5)
  - Liberty Hyde Bailey, Ms of Coulter's biography. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Hugo De Vries, Ms of Coulter's biography. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Rafinesque, Ms of Coulter's biography. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The International Mission of Universities. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The New Spirit. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Book reviews for Science: General Botany by C. Stuart Gager Flora of the Panama Canal Zone by Paul C. Stanley. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Report: International Congress of Plant Sciences. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Report: Philadelphia Symposium. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Report: American Electrotheraputic Association, 37th Annual Meeting. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Report: Winter Potatoes (about Dr. F. E. Denny) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Daily Science News Bulletin, May 15, 1926 (notice of an article by Coulter in Science.) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - List of Books from the Library of John M. Coulter. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Part of a letter, unaddressed and unsigned (8 pages, unnumbered) describing "a short visit to Pootoo." (Probably to Caroline Coulter). (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Letter: C. F. Cowan to Leila Garritt, with Photograph (unidentified). (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous fragments and sheets: most in JMC's hand, but back of one drawing bears note with signature M.S.C. (Box 4, Folder 25)